翻 译   @一个Delpy&时间轴调整   @EthanYip
他喜欢那台旧相机
He loves that old camera.
快来 杨
Come on, Yang.
马上
One second.
别忘了过来一起拍
Don't forget to join us.
记得的
I will.
看这里一下
Look here for a second.
你在做什么呢 快来
What are you doing? Come on.
过来 哥哥
Come on, gege.
黄色春分 这是新品吗
Yellow Equinox. Is that a new blend?
应该是吧
I think so.
我应该可以给你做个口味接近的
I'm sure I can make you something close to it.
你知道它用的是哪种茶叶吗
Do you know what kind of tea leaves?
哦 不是 不是那种茶
Oh, no. No, no. It's not this kind of tea.
我是想买那种茶粉
I'm looking for your crystallized teas.
不好意思 我没有茶粉
Ah. Sorry, I... I don't carry tea crystals.
你一个开茶店的怎么能没有茶粉呢
How can you be a tea shop and not carry tea crystals?
我好失望
How frustrating.
我给你配一种口味接近的吧
Why don't you let me make you something that might be close?
不用了 这真是…我要走了
No. No, no, no. This is... I have to go.
感谢光临
Thanks for coming in.
爸爸什么时候回家
When's Daddy coming home?
很快
Soon.
他总是很晚回来
He's always late.
我有时候也会很晚回家
Well, I'm late sometimes, too.
你知道 我接下去几周会很忙
And, you know, I've got a busy few weeks coming up, so...
我知道 杨会在的
I know. Yang will be here.
爸爸也会在
So will Daddy.
美香
Mika.
美香 别对他太苛刻
Mika? Don't be too hard on him.
他跟我说 快关门的时候
He told me there was a rush of customers
来了一拨客人
towards the end of the day.
这对他来说是好事 他需要生意
That's good news for Daddy. He needed that.
我觉得饭很好吃
I loved that meal.
你喜欢那个辣椒酱吗
Did you like the gochujang sauce?
- 我喜欢  - 是我做的
- I did. - I made it.
你说过了
You mentioned that.
这是她第一次做
It was her first time.
所以是你把材料放到碗里
So you put the ingredients in the bowl
然后是你搅拌的
and you mixed them all together?
对
Yeah.
好吃吧
It's good, huh?
真的很好吃 妹妹
It was really wonderful, mei mei.
谢谢
Thank you.
下次我要给胡萝卜去丝
Next time, I'm gonna Juliet the carrots.
是切丝
Julienne.
不过我不会让你切的
And no, you're not.
美香长大得好快
Mika's growing up so fast.
她一直问我们为什么总是这么忙
She keeps asking why we're always busy.
她理解的
She understands.
- 而且杨…  - 不 她不理解
- And Yang is... - No, she doesn't.
我感觉…
I feel like...
我不知道 我…
I don't know. I...
我不想有遗憾
I don't want to regret.
我会多抽出点时间来的
Um... Um, I'll make more time.
我会的 我保证
I will. I promise.
你知道我不会把这个负担强加给你的吧
You know I'm not putting this on you, right?
应该会吧
Hmm. Sort of.
- 我不会的  - 我开玩笑的
- I'm not. - I'm teasing.
我只是想让我们成为一个团队
I just want us to be a team.
成为一个家
A family.
开始
Starting
点火
Ignite
开始
Starting
重置
Reset
开始
Starting
点火
Ignite
开始
Starting
重置
Reset
开始
Starting
欢迎四口之家
Welcome, families of four,
参加我们每月的舞蹈大赛
to our monthly dance-off.
今晚共有三万家庭参与角逐
We have over 30,000 families competing tonight.
你们准备好了吗
Are you ready?
保持同步
Stay in sync.
踩点增加
Precision points added.
开始飞行
Take flight.
准备格斗
Ready for combat.
开始格斗
Fight time.
第一阶段完成
Level one complete.
三千组家庭被淘汰
继续努力
Stay together.
保持稳定
Steady.
前方同步加分
Sync bonus coming up.
搭车动作
The hitchhiker.
开始
Go.
过渡动作
Transition.
累积炸药
Collect the TNT.
引爆
Detonate.
微笑 合照时间
Smile. It's time for family portrait.
开始地震
Earthquake.
龙卷风来袭
Tornado time.
第二阶段完成
Level two complete.
九千组家庭被淘汰
耐力考验
Stamina round.
继续坚持
Keep up.
导演&编剧  郭共达
保持同步
Stay in sync.
淘汰
Terminated.
亲爱的
Babe! Babe!
不是我 是…
It wasn't me. It was...
才不是我呢 美香?
It wasn't me! Mika?
不是我 是爸爸!
Not me! It was Daddy!
对
Mm-hmm.
这已经是我们的最好成绩了
That's the furthest we've ever gone.
确实
That's true.
杨 我们已经淘汰了
Yang, we're... we're out.
杨? 杨!
Yang? Yang!
- 杨!  - 杨?
- Yang! - Yang?
杨 之 后
我们应该还有三年的保修期
It looks like we have three years left
但他们不接我电话 所以…
on the warranty, but they're not answering, so...
- 你不能直接过去吗  - 可以 我准备去了
- Can't you just go there? - Yeah, I'm going to,
但我都不知道那个店还在不在
but I don't know if the store is even there anymore.
我查了一下 已经查不到了
I did a search. I can't find them anywhere.
你给"兄弟&姐妹"打电话了吗
Did you call Brothers & Sisters?
我们不是直接从那里买的
We didn't buy from them directly, so...
所以他们不能提供保修?
They won't honor the warranty?
不行 保修要找"第二个孩子"
No, the warranty is with Second Siblings.
我就说我们应该买个新的
I told you we should've just bought a new one.
他是新的 算是吧
He was new. I mean, practically.
他是翻新的
He's refurbished.
认证翻新的
Certified refurbished.
而且他之前只用了五天而已 五天
And he'd only been in use for five days. Five days.
- 我们就省了…  - 但现在 他…
- And we saved... - But now he...
算了 快去把他修好吧
Never mind. Let's just get him fixed.
嗯
Yeah.
你要送美香去学校
You need to get Mika to school.
美香 快来 我们要走了
Mika, come on, we need to go!
美香?
Mika?
- 美香?  - 杨怎么了
- Mika? - What happened to Yang?
哦 你好 嗯…
Oh, hi. Um...
我不知道
I don't know.
他昨晚宕机了 没法重启
He... He shut down last night. Won't restart.
- 这种情况之前发生过吗  - 没有
- Has this happened before? - No.
你认识维修工吗
You got a technician?
他还在保修期内
He's still under warranty.
我是不会把他送回"兄弟&姐妹"的
I wouldn't take him back to Brothers & Sisters.
他们只会让你把他回收
They're just going to try to get you to recycle him
然后换个新的给你 你知道为什么的
for a new model. You know why.
我没准备把他送那儿去
I'm not taking him there.
保修是在另一家店
The warranty's with another store.
你不是直接买的官方的吗
You didn't buy him direct?
不是 那个…他有官方认证的
No. No, uh, he's certified.
我要去叫下美香
I have to go and get Mika.
美香还在这儿吗
Oh, Mika's still here?
她看到杨宕机的样子了吗
Did she see Yang all dead-eyed?
- 她会吓到的吧  - 嗯
- I bet it freaked her out. - Yeah.
听我说 我认识伍德伯里的一个维修工
Listen, I got a technician in Woodbury.
大老远过去也值
It's worth the trek.
我把他的信息发给你
I'm going to send you his info.
不用了 我就带他去"快修"吧
No, I'll just... I'll take him to Quick Fix
要是我搞不定的话
if I can't figure it out.
傻子才去那里 别送他去那
That place is for morons. Don't take him there.
我认识的那个人修一下只要三分之一的价钱
My guy will fix him for a third of the cost.
你跟拉斯说是我让你去的
You tell Russ I sent ya.
好吧 我该走了 谢谢
Okay. Okay, got to go. Thank you.
美香 美香
Mika? Mika?
走吧 孩子 我们得走了
Come on, kiddo, we gotta boogie.
我不想去上学 我想和杨待在一起
I don't want to go to school. I want to be with Yang.
美香 我们拖得越久
Mika, the longer we wait,
杨的情况就越糟糕
the worse it's gonna be for Yang.
什么意思
What do you mean?
他会开始分解
He'll start decomposing.
什么
What?
来吧 我们该走了
Come on, we gotta go.
美香 快
Mika, now.
对了 美香今天都跟我一起
FYI, Mika's going to be with me for the day.
为什么 怎么了
Why? What happened?
因为她刚刚拒绝去上学
Well, you know, she just refused and
我就不拽她去学校了
I wasn't gonna drag her inside.
美香
Mika?
说话
Answer me.
妈妈 我不能去 我要和杨待在一起
Mom, I can't. I want to be with Yang.
没关系 亲爱的
It's okay, darling.
我只是想听听你的声音
I just wanted to hear your voice.
你要听爸爸的话 乖乖的好吗
You need to listen to Dad and be good and calm, okay?
杨会好起来吗
Is Yang going to be better?
嗯 他会…
Yes, he's gonna be...
其实我们也不确定 但…
Well, we don't know for sure, but...
这是什么意思
What do you mean?
是啊 你这是什么意思
Yeah, what do you mean?
我们没法承诺 但是美香 听着
We can't make any promises, but, Mika, listen,
如果你今天都乖乖地听话
if you can be good and calm for the rest of the day,
我会给你一个惊喜
I'm gonna bring you a surprise.
什么惊喜
What?
你刚刚就承诺了要给她一个惊喜
You just promised her a surprise.
- 是什么呀 妈妈  - 那不一样
- What is it, Mom? - That's different.
妈妈 是什么呀
Mom, what is it?
我不是想要…
I wasn't trying to...
谢谢你今天休息一天
I appreciate you taking the day off.
- 妈妈?  - 亲爱的
- Mom? - Honey,
要乖 听爸爸的话
be good and listen to Dad.
我得挂了
Oh, I need to go.
我要准备我的报告了 回聊
I have to get ready for my presentation. We'll talk.
她要送我什么呀 爸爸
What is she gonna get me, Dad?
我不知道
I have no idea.
我觉得我知道
I think I know.
不要对具体的东西抱有希望
Just don't get your hopes up for anything specific.
哥哥  我知道她要给我什么东西
Gege, I know what she's gonna get me.
你好?
Excuse me?
- 你好?  - 有什么事吗
- Excuse me? - Can I help you?
嗯 我想问你能不能…
Yeah, I was wondering if you could...
我买了…
I purchased a...
这里之前是可以给收养的中国小孩
This used to be a store where you could buy, uh,
买一个哥哥或姐姐的店
an older sibling for Chinese adoptions.
名字叫"第二个孩子"
It was called Second Siblings.
我们这是卖鱼和鱼缸的
We sell fish and tanks.
嗯 我看出来了
Yeah, I can see,
那你知道之前那家店怎么了吗
but do you know what happened to that shop?
在我之前的那家店是卖内存的
Before my store, they sold memory.
纪念本 是这么说的吗
Memory-balia. Is that how you say it, memory-balia?
- 纪念品  - 纪念品 对
- Memorabilia. - Memorabilia. Yeah, memories.
不卖机器人吗
But no technos?
不卖 我不知道他那家店之前是卖什么的
No, I'm not sure what it was before that.
好吧 谢谢
All right, thank you.
美香?
Mika?
美香 来 我们走了
Mika. Mika, come on, let's go.
我想要一条鱼
I want a fish.
哥哥 这是泡泡
Gege? Meet Puffy.
所以这是黑匣子出了问题
Uh, it's a black box issue, okay?
但根据规定 我们是不可以
Uh, so by law, we're not allowed
改动内部机核的 不好意思
to tamper with the, uh, core interior, unfortunately.
那你们能干嘛
So what is it that you do here?
我们由"兄弟&姐妹"官方认证
We are certified with Brothers & Sisters, Incorporated,
可以修理或更换最常使用的
to repair or replace up to 12 parts
十二个部件
most commonly in need of service.
你可以看一下那边的
If you want to take a gander there
十二点诊断图
at the 12-point diagnostic.
但你这个诊断只是…
Yeah, but your diagnostics is just...
我们把杨送去给认证的分析师进行了分析
Um, well, we hooked up Yang to our certified analyzer,
十二个部件都正常
and, uh, all 12 parts were in working order,
但从读数上能看出
however, the readout did indicate that there was
他存在机核故障 所以…
a core malfunction, unfortunately, so...
所以什么 你们无能为力?
So what? So there's nothing you can do?
不是 我们还是可以提供一些服务的
Oh, there's a couple things we can do here.
我们可以把他回收给"兄弟&姐妹"
Um, we can have him recycled at Brothers & Sisters.
如果在他开始分解前回收的话
Uh, if you do so before he begins to decompose,
你会得到一张1000美元的新机优惠券
you'll get $1,000 off on a new model, which is great.
如果你不想回收他
Uh, if you don't want to have him recycled,
我也理解 我们也可以
which I completely understand, um, we are equipped
把他的头部和喉咙更换成虚拟助手
to turn his head and his voice box into a virtual assistant,
并为您整修剩下的部分
and we'd salvage the remaining parts for ya.
什么
What?
但我们要把机核送到…
But we would have to send the core to, uh,
"兄弟&姐妹"
Brothers & Sisters.
不不不 这是不可能的
No, no, no. That's not gonna happen.
把他还给我 我再去别的地方问问
Now, just give him back to me, and I'll get a second opinion.
好的 没问题
Oh, sure. Of course.
那诊断费一共是250美元 谢谢
Uh, so that'll be 250 for the diagnostics, please.
你在开玩笑吧
You're kidding me.
不好意思 没开玩笑
Unfortunately, no.
听起来不太妙
That doesn't sound good.
我知道
I know.
你跟美香是怎么说的
What did you tell Mika?
我说我们要去别家问问
I said we were getting a second opinion.
这事比我预期的要麻烦
It's already taken longer than I expected.
- 爸爸  - 你好 美香
- Daddy? - Hi, Mika.
你好
Hi.
你还好吗
Are you okay?
不太好 我有了一条小鱼
No. I got a fish.
是吗
You did?
- 是吗  - 嗯
- She did? - Yeah.
是一条小…我过会儿跟你解释
Yeah, it's a little... I'll explain later.
我们快到了
We're almost there.
好吧 保持联系
All right. Keep me posted.
好的
Okay.
再见 美香
Bye, Mika.
再见 和杨说再见
Bye. Say bye to Yang.
再见 杨
Bye, Yang.
这是内部机核故障
It is an interior core problem.
是的 我们已经知道了
Yeah, we knew that already.
我需要你的允许才能打开机核
I need your permission to break open the core.
这是违法的
It's against the law.
这就是…公司吓唬人罢了
It's just... It's a bunch of corporate bullshit.
你知道规矩是谁定的吗
Do you know who made that a law?
"兄弟&姐妹"公司
Brothers & Sisters.
他们只是想保护自己的间谍装置
They're just trying to protect their spyware.
你把他送去回收了
You recycle that,
他们就会得到你家庭的大量数据
they will have so much data on your family,
可有你头疼的了
it'll make your head spin.
我不感兴趣
I'm not interested.
那是你的损失
Your loss.
你保证会修好他的
You promised to fix him.
美香 我让你在外面等
Mika, I said wait outside.
你说他会没事的
You said he was gonna be fine.
快点 你得做个决定
Come on, man. You gotta make a decision.
或许这是一件好事
Maybe this is a good thing.
这怎么会是件好事呢
How is this a good thing?
杨…
Yang has been...
杨真的太好了
Yang has been wonderful.
我们会非常想念他的
And we'd all miss him terribly,
但我们过分依赖他了
but we've been over-reliant on him.
我们买杨是为了让美香
We bought Yang to connect Mika
更亲近她的中国血统 而不是抚养她长大
to her Chinese heritage, not to raise her.
是 但我们在杨身上花了很多钱
Yeah, but we spent a lot of money on Yang.
我不会…
I mean, I'm not gonna...
因为他不止是教美香中国小知识
...you know, feel bad if he does more for Mika
而感到对不起他
than teach her Chinese fun facts.
他做的不止这些 但这不是重点
He does a lot more than that, but you're missing the point.
重点是什么
What's the point?
如果我们没法把杨修好
If we can't fix Yang,
我们也不会再买一个给美香了
we're not gonna buy another sibling for Mika.
那样实在是太…
That would just be...
奇怪了
strange.
况且我们也买不起
And we can't afford it anyway.
所以我们要多参与进来
So we need to be more involved.
比现在参与得更多
More than we are now.
而且不止是抚养她长大
And not just in raising her,
还有让她亲近她的文化和传统
in connecting Mika to her culture and heritage.
那就是我们的责任了
Like, that will be on us.
所以我们要有这个准备和意愿
So we need to be ready and willing.
(春分)
妹妹 你怎么了
Mei mei,what's wrong?
没事
Nothing.
你看起来不像是没事
Your face says something different.
有几个小孩
Just some kids.
你班上的吗
In your class?
不是 休息的时候
No, kids at recess.
他们问我父母的事
They were asking about my real parents.
这样啊
I see.
那你怎么说的
And what did you say?
我跟他们说了我的妈妈和爸爸
I told them about Mom and Dad,
然后他们说 "他们不是你的亲生父母"
and they said, "No, your real parents."
他们说爸爸妈妈不是我真正的父母
They said Mom and Dad weren't really my parents. Not really.
你相信吗
Do you believe them?
我是说 他们是我们父母 但…
I mean, they're our parents, but...
我们不是
we're not,
你知道的 他们不是…
you know, they're not...
不是真正的
Not really.
妹妹
Mei mei.
就是这里
Here it is.
你看这里
Take a look at this.
这棵树受伤了吗
Is the tree hurt?
没有 这里将有奇迹发生
No. Something wonderful is happening here.
什么奇迹
What?
你看 这根树枝来自另一棵树
You see, this branch is from a different tree.
是吗
It is?
是的 而现在 它就要成为这棵树的一部分了
Yes, but now it's becoming an actual part of this tree.
没有吧 只是假装而已
Not really, though. It's just pretend.
你为什么这么说
Why do you say that?
因为它只是被绑在这棵树上了
Because it's just taped to the tree.
哦 对 现在看起来是这样 对吗
Oh, right. It looks like that, doesn't it?
来 我们找一棵已经连上的
Here, let's find one that's already attached.
妹妹
Mei mei.
看到这根树枝了吗
See this branch?
这根树枝同样来自另一棵树
This branch is also from another tree.
但你看 你就像这根树枝一样
But look, you're connected to Mom and Dad,
和爸爸妈妈连在了一起
just like this branch.
你是这棵家庭树的一部分 真的
You're a part of the family tree. For real.
那你也是
Then so are you.
他们为什么要这么做
Why do they do it?
为什么要把树枝移到另一棵树上
Why do they move branches to different trees?
这叫嫁接
It's called grafting.
这样做可以创造新的东西
They do it to make something new.
有些你喜欢吃的苹果
Some of the apples you love
就是通过嫁接不同品种的树产生的
were produced by combining different trees.
这是一项古老的技术
It's an ancient technique
早在4000多年前就在中国使用了
that was used in China over 4,000 years ago.
- 一个中国小知识  - 对
- A Chinese fun fact. - Yes.
但你要知道 嫁接的两棵树都很重要
But you should know that both trees are important.
不只是这棵 这根树枝来自的那棵树也很重要
Not just this one, but the one from this branch, too.
你另一个家庭对你来说也很重要
Your other family tree is also a vital part of who you are.
你明白吗
Do you understand?
我想和爸爸一起去
I want to go with Dad.
不行 你今天要去上学
No, kiddo, you need to go to school today.
但是杨! 我要见杨!
But Yang! I wanna see Yang!
你的泡泡呢
Hey, what about your Pup-Pup?
你不想拿给你朋友看吗
Don't you want to show your friends?
杨
Yang.
杨很快就会回家了
Yang's gonna be home soon.
他好点了吗
Is he better?
到时候就知道了
We'll see.
但你今天要去上学
But you need to go to school.
杨会希望你去上学的 为了哥哥去学校吧
Yang would want that. Do it for gege.
他会希望我带泡泡给他们看
He'd want me to show my Pup-Pup.
好了 我出门了
All right, I'm heading out.
好 记得告诉我进展
Okay. Let me know how it goes.
嗯
Will do.
你的包 来吧
Your bag. Come on.
我们一直都知道 有些机器人
We've always known that some bots
安装了间谍装置
are equipped with spyware.
特别是外国的 现在我们有证据了
Especially the foreign ones. And now we have proof.
现在? 所以你之前从来没见过这东西
Now? So you've never seen these before.
有什么关系呢 东西就这东西
What does it matter? It is what it is.
你看过录像了吗
Have you looked at the recordings?
没有
No.
没看过 我可是支持隐私权的
No! I'm pro-privacy.
我可以看看里面有什么吗
Can I see what's on here?
你需要一个特殊的读卡器
You'll need a special reader.
这种接口我从来没见过
The connectors, they're nothing I've seen before.
这可是很高端的东西
This is some high-level shit, man.
这真的是…
I mean, this is...
不好意思 我只是想理清头绪
Sorry, I'm... I'm just trying to wrap my head around it.
- 好烦  - 确实
- It's disturbing. - Yes.
确实让人心烦
It is disturbing.
该醒过来了 哥们
It's time to wake up, man.
那我去哪买这种读卡器
So how do I buy a reader that I can see what's on this?
这种读卡器没的卖的
No one's selling a reader for that.
你得找人专门
You'll have to have one
改装一个适配这种接口的
specifically modified for those connectors.
行吧
Great.
好吧 我告诉你一个人
Okay, I'm gonna give you a name.
没有电话 但这是地址
There's no number, but this is where you find them.
我要给你多少钱
How much do I owe you?
我说了 我收钱修东西而已
Like I said, I get paid to fix things.
谢谢
Thank you.
那我把杨带回去了
I guess I'll take Yang back.
我跟你说
I'll tell you what.
你为什么不先看了再说
Why don't... Why don't you look what's on there first?
如果里面的东西不太好
If it's something bad, disturbing,
你可能都不想再让这个机器人进家门了
you might not want this bot in your house anymore.
你可以带走他 但他会开始分解
You can take him, but also, he's gonna start decomposing.
分解剩下的也不值几个钱
You won't get as much value for him.
我可以把他接在模拟器上
I can keep him hooked up on the simulator
等你多了解一些情况
until you know more.
你是乔治的朋友 对吧
You're a friend of George, right?
对
Yeah.
抱歉 她在开会
Sorry, she's in a meeting,
但我可以为您留言
but I'd be happy to pass on a message.
好 麻烦告诉她…
Yeah, could you just tell her...
喂? 还在吗
Uh, hello? Are you still there?
算了 没事 我一会儿再打给她
You know what, it's all right. I'll talk to her later.
好的 需要她一会儿给您回电吗
Great. Should I have her call you back?
不用 没事 谢谢
No. No, it's all right. Thank you.
有人说我可以找你
I was told I could talk to you.
我找麦克斯·沃克 但他们说…
I was looking for Max Walker, but they mentioned...
我不感兴趣
Oh, I'm not interested.
什么
Sorry?
你是来谈什么阴谋论的吗
Are you here to talk some conspiracy shit?
不是 拉斯说我可以…
No. No, Russ told me that I could...
拉斯? 好吧 你是他们的人
Russ? Oh, man, you're one of them.
真不敢相信他们会让你进来
I can't believe they let you back here.
我不是他们的人 我…
I'm not one of them. I...
我有这个东西
I have this.
他说麦克斯可以帮上忙
I was told Max might be able to help me with it.
那是什么
What is that?
拉斯说这是间谍装置
Russ said it's spyware.
这是从哪儿来的
Where did you find it?
在杨体内发现的
It was inside Yang.
他是我们的…
And... he's our...
我们收养了女儿之后买的他 她是中国人
We bought him after we adopted our daughter. She's Chinese.
嗯哼
Mm-hmm.
杨宕机之后
And my neighbor recommended Russ
我邻居给我推荐的拉斯 拉斯打开了…
after Yang shut down, and Russ broke in...
我…抱歉 能不能让我…
Can I... Sorry. Can I?
当然
Yeah, sure.
我的天呐 这可不是什么间谍装置
Holy shit, this isn't spyware.
我敢肯定这是内存条
I'm pretty sure it's a memory bank.
内存条可以让机器人
The memory banks allowed the technos
每天记录几秒的时间
to record a few seconds each day.
实验室之前一直在研究
The labs were trying to understand
机器人如何判断是否值得记忆
what technos considered memorable.
但研究没有成果
But the research was uncovered,
整个项目因为侵犯隐私法
the whole project was shut down
而立即被关停了
immediately for violating privacy laws.
那我该怎么做
So what do I do?
我不骗你 这…
Oh, I'm not gonna lie. This...
这东西非常重要
This is a big deal.
如果这是控制器的话 拉斯就说对了
If it's the regulator, then Russ is right.
他没法再启动了
He's not gonna turn on.
我跟你说实话
I'm just being honest with you.
但他的存在
But his existence,
杨的存在
Yang's existence would be
对我们博物馆
an invaluable contribution to this museum
以及对理解机器人智慧
and just to the whole understanding
会有巨大的贡献
of techno-sapiens.
所以现在的问题应该是
So I guess the real question's gonna be,
我们要用多少钱向你买
what do we pay you to have Yang and his memories
杨和他的记忆
in our collection?
能再给我一份这个吗
Could I have another one of these, please?
接听电话
Answer call.
- 你好  - 你好 美香还好吗
- Hey. - Hey. How's Mika?
她在隔壁
She's next door.
隔壁? 乔治家吗
Next door? At George's?
对
Yep.
为什么
Why?
因为你不在家 而我要工作
Because you're not here, and I have work to do.
我在照顾杨
I'm taking care of Yang.
是吗
Is that what you're doing?
是的
Yes.
所以你就这样把她丢到隔壁去了?
So you just dropped her off over there?
不是 他的两个女儿找她过去玩
No, his daughters invited her over to play.
你不要再对乔治这么苛刻了
You need to stop being so hard on George.
他挺喜欢你的 也很爱帮忙
He likes you, and he's being really helpful.
他的孩子是克隆人
His kids are clones.
我不想再谈这个了
I don't want to talk about this again.
而且他看比赛的时候会把脸画花
And he paints his face for sporting events.
- 你有什么问题吗  - 他有什么问题吗
- What is wrong with you? - What's wrong with him?
别这样了 行吗
You need to stop. Okay?
拉面好吃吗
How's the ramen?
很治愈
It's, um, soothing.
是吧 看出来了
Yeah, I can see that.
你在吃什么
What are you having?
拉面
Ramen.
是吗 有意思
Really? That's funny.
有意思吗
Is it?
有点 你不觉得吗
Sort of, don't you think?
杨就快修好了吗
Are you any closer to getting Yang fixed?
这已经是你带他去的第三个地方了
This is the third place you've taken him to.
他其实还在修理店
Well, he's actually still at the repair shop.
我把一个部件拿给
I'm, uh, having a part examined.
专家检查
By a specialist.
那他很快就能重新启动了吗
So is he gonna be up and running again soon?
不确定 你知道 这东西很复杂的
I'm not sure. You know, it's... it's complicated.
是美香回来了 我得挂了
That's Mika. I got to go.
和其他读卡器一样使用
Functions like any other reader.
使用起来应该很方便
Should be intuitive.
需要输入什么密码吗
Do I need a code?
对 你买杨的时候应该有一张
Yeah, there should be a certification card
认证卡
that came with Yang.
上面有一个序列号和一个识别码
There's a serial number and a pin on it.
还有 依照我们的约定
Also, per our agreement,
你明天要把杨的躯体带来
you'll need to bring Yang's body here tomorrow.
- 越快越好  - 好的
- Sooner the better. - Yes.
要是拉斯试图更换部件
I wouldn't be surprised
或是偷拿原装部件
if Russ is trying to replace parts
我是不会惊讶的
and steal the originals.
我们会把杨的躯体以生物状态保存在这里
We will keep Yang's body preserved here in a bio-state
与此同时 你去查看内存
while you go and review the memories
决定下一步该怎么办
and decide what you want to do next.
好的 谢谢
Okay. Yeah. Thank you.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我一生都致力于理解机器人智慧
I've dedicated my life to understanding techno-sapiens.
这是…天赐的礼物
This... This is a gift.
我想要
I want to be
像风一样
Just like the wind
在空中飘着
Just flowing in the air
在空地飘着
Flowing in open space
杨教你的吗
Yang taught you that?
是啊 这是他最喜欢的歌
Uh-huh. It's his favorite song.
你喜欢吗
Do you like it?
很喜欢
I love it.
嗨
Hey.
美香这么晚还没睡
Mika's up late.
她睡不着
She couldn't sleep.
你要去哪儿吗
You going somewhere?
布伦达要我一起到公司
Brenda's meeting me at the office.
我们准备通宵工作
We're gonna stay overnight and work.
进度慢了
We're behind.
对不起 我没有早点回来
Sorry I wasn't here earlier.
没事
It's fine.
明天你要送美香去学校
You'll need to take Mika to school
帮她准备好各种东西
and get her ready for the day.
你能做到吗
Do you think you can do that?
当然可以
Yeah, of course.
好的 我得走了
All right. I need to go.
我们…我们之间没事吧
Are we... Are we okay?
所以那个部件怎么了
So what did the part reveal?
部件?
The part?
那个部件
The part.
专家?
The specialist?
哦 对
Oh. Oh, yeah, yeah.
嗯…
Um...
我们应该很快就知道了
You... We should know something soon.
我得走了
I need to go.
尽量睡一会儿
Try and get some sleep if you can.
序列号 733951137CM99
Serial 733951137CM99.
识别号 279321
Pin 279321.
播放
Play.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
重放
Repeat.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
播放
Play.
我想被爱…
I want to be loved...
一 二 三 四
One, two, three, four.
- 五  - 五
- Five. - Five.
- 六  - 六
- Six. - Six.
- 七  - 七
- Seven. - Seven.
八 九 十
Eight. Nine. Ten.
妹妹 妹妹
Mei mei. Mei mei.
走过来 妹妹 走过来
Walk to me, Mei mei. Walk to me.
小心
Careful.
(美香的小店)
真棒
Wonderful.
- 彩虹  - 彩虹
- Cai hong. - Cai hong.
他们知道你不是故意的
They know you didn't mean it.
你好 妹妹
Ni hao, Mei mei.
爸爸
Daddy.
Daddy!
不好意思 没事吧
Sorry, is everything okay?
我正要出来喝水
I'm getting some water.
要我帮你吗
Do you want me to?
你在看电影吗
Are you watching a movie?
对
I am.
你在看什么
What are you watching?
一个…
Just a...
一个纪录片
Just a documentary.
是关于茶的吗
Is it about tea?
对
Yeah.
把你无聊得都哭了吗
Is it boring you to tears?
我们去倒水喝吧
Let's get you some water.
我来吧
I'll do it.
好
Okay.
你平时都会这样吗
Is this something you do?
半夜出来倒水喝
Do you get yourself water in the middle of the night?
哥哥常常和我一起
Gege usually comes with me.
这样吗 所以你会把他叫醒?
Is that right? So you'd wake him up?
他需要睡觉吗
Does he sleep?
他不需要
No, I don't think so.
我一般只需要叫一声 哥哥
I usually just say, "Gege."
不用很大声 因为即使我悄悄地说
Not very loudly because he can hear me
他都能听见
even when I whisper.
我说 "哥哥 我想去倒水喝"
I say, "Gege, I want to get some water."
他就会在走廊和我碰头
Then he joins me in the hallway,
然后我们悄悄地走到厨房
and we walk quietly to the kitchen.
你为什么不让他去倒水给你喝呢
Why don't you just ask him to get you a glass of water?
这样你就不用下床了
Then you can stay in bed.
我喜欢自己倒水喝
I like getting my own water.
什么叫你要把他拿回去
What do you mean you want him back?
就是我要把他拿回去的意思
I mean I want him back.
麦克斯给你做读卡器了吗
Did Max make the reader for you?
麦克斯已经不在那里了
Max isn't there anymore.
- 那他在哪里  - 我不知道
- Where is he? - I don't know.
我猜他是被抓了
I bet they took him.
不敢相信 他们终于抓住他了
I can't believe they finally got him.
拜托 让我把杨带走
Please, just let me have Yang back.
给我一个解释
I want an explanation.
杨是我们的 我…
Yang belongs to us. I...
我不需要向你解释
don't need to give you an explanation.
会没事的
It'll be all right.
我的天 我好喜欢文化机器人
God, I love cultural technos.
而且在他们被用于
And since they're used
收养和语言学习后
for adoptions and language learning,
他们并不需要进行多大的改变
they haven't had to change much over the years.
不需要变得更快或更强
No need to be faster or stronger.
这里有些损坏
There's some damage here.
该死的拉斯 他强行把他打开了
Damn Russ just hacked his way into the core.
其实是有正确的打开方式的
There's a proper way of opening it.
所以 如果你不介意的话
So if you don't mind,
我们要对他进行全面检查
we're just gonna do a full check-up,
然后尽我们所能把他修复好
and we're gonna restore Yang as best we can.
那真是太好了
Oh, that would be great.
修复并不能帮他重启
It won't help with his off state,
但可以有利于保存
but it should help with his preservation.
播放
Play.
重放
Repeat.
播放
Play.
快来 杨
Come on, Yang.
马上
One second.
我的傻丫头
My silly girl.
傻丫头
Silly girl.
他喜欢那台旧相机
He loves that old camera.
快来 杨
Come on, Yang.
傻丫头
Silly girl.
他喜欢那台旧相机
He loves that old camera.
快来 杨
Come on, Yang.
马上
One second.
别忘了过来一起拍
Don't forget to join us.
记得的
I will.
他喜欢那台旧相机
He loves that old camera.
快来 杨
Come on, Yang.
马上
One second.
别忘了过来一起拍
Don't forget to join us.
记得的
I will.
傻丫头
Silly girl.
看这里一下
Just look here for one second.
你在干什么 快来
What are you doing? Come on.
快来 哥哥
Come on, gege.
你喜欢茶的什么
What do you like about tea?
你是说什么味道吗
Do you mean the taste of tea?
可能吧 你是因为喜欢茶的味道吗
Maybe. Is the taste why you like tea?
有点关系吧
It has something to do with it.
所以你把你的一生都献给了茶?
Is it why you've given your life to tea?
把我的一生献给茶
Given my life to tea,
这么说感觉太严肃了
well, that sounds pretty serious.
这不是一件严肃的事吗
Is it not serious?
我想是因为我学会了品茶
I guess I've acquired a taste for tea.
但这不是我感兴趣的原因
But it's not why I became interested.
感兴趣
Interested.
我想一开始吸引我的
I think what I was really drawn to
原因是…
at the beginning was...
我想一开始
I think what I was really drawn to
吸引我的原因是茶这个概念
at the beginning was the idea of tea.
茶这个概念
The idea of tea.
对 我在大学的时候
Yeah, I saw this old documentary
看了一部老纪录片
when I was in college.
那是二十世纪的
It was from the 20th century.
它讲的是一个人
And it was about this man
在寻找中国最好的茶
searching for the best tea in China.
它讲的是一个人在寻找中国最好的茶
It's about a man searching for the best tea in China.
中国是茶起源的地方
China is where tea started.
对 你应该知道许多
Yes, I'm sure you have
中国关于茶的小知识
lots of interesting facts about tea in China.
是的
I do.
你想听我说几个吗
Would you like to hear some of them?
下次吧
Maybe another time.
不好意思 你刚刚在说
I'm sorry, you were saying
一个人去找茶
about the man searching for tea.
对 对
Yeah. Yeah.
其实 就是这样
Yeah, actually, I think that's it.
我觉得是他的寻觅促使我这么做的
I think it was his searching that compelled me.
寻觅这种虚幻的东西
You know, the pursuit of this illusive thing,
这一过程与泥土
this process that was connected to the soil,
与植被 与天气 与生活方式相连
to the plants, to the weather, and to a way of life.
与生活方式
To a way of life.
所以这是你喜欢茶的地方
So that's what you like about tea?
是这种寻觅 而不是它的味道
The search, not so much the taste.
不不 味道也是
No, no, no, the taste, too.
电影里…
There's this, uh...
电影里有这么一段
There's this part in the film,
这段很有意思 那个人
it's a great part, where the man
在向他的德国朋友解释
is explaining to his German friend
为什么茶的味道那么难以形容
why it's so difficult for him to describe the taste of tea.
他说 "这是无法用语言形容的
He says, "There's no language for it.
"没有任何词汇能够充分表达
"There are no words to adequately express
"茶的玄妙"
"the mysterious nature of tea."
然后他的德国朋友
And his German friend,
站在他身边
who's just standing right beside him
捧着一杯茶说
with a cup of tea, says,
"对 但我会想象
"Yes, but I imagine things
"走在森林中
"like you are walking through a forest,
"地上有落叶
"and there are leaves on the ground,
"刚下过雨 现在雨停了
"and it just had rained, and the rain has stopped,
"空气潮湿 而你就这么走着
and it's damp, and you walk,
"不知怎么的 这种感觉都在茶里了"
"and somehow, that is all in this tea."
我太喜欢这段了
I mean, I loved that so much.
太喜欢了
I loved that so much.
"不知怎么的 这种感觉都在茶里了"
"Somehow, that is all in this tea."
我看了一遍又一遍
God, I watched it over and over again.
我想看看这部电影
I would like to watch this movie.
也许我们可以一起看
Well, maybe we can do it together.
那好啊
Yes. That would be nice.
所以你相信吗
So do you believe it?
相信什么
What's that?
一茶一世界
That a cup of tea can contain a world?
茶里可以品出一个地方 一段时间?
That you could taste a place, a time?
我们来试一试 怎么样
Let's put it to the test, shall we?
先闻一闻
So you want to smell it first.
你知道 这里不止有
You know, there's not just
味道和气味 还有历史
flavor and the aroma, there's history, too.
你知道吗 传统上来说
You know, traditionally,
茶铺都是家族
tea shops that were family businesses
一代一代…
passed down from one generation to an...
Were passed down from...
传承的 这你知道的
generation to, you know this,
传承的
from generation to generation.
或许是时候我教你这一行了
Maybe it's time I started teaching you the trade.
看看我们能不能一起品味世界
Let's see if we can taste the world together.
一口喝完
Drink it all at once.
你觉得怎么样
What did you think?
我不确定我有没有品出森林的味道
I'm not sure if I can taste the forest.
那你品出了什么吗
Do you taste anything?
也许我没有语言来形容
Maybe I haven't the language for it.
我希望中国茶对我来说不止是知识而已
I wish Chinese tea wasn't just about facts for me.
这是什么意思
What do you mean?
我喜欢看你泡茶的样子
I like watching the way you make tea.
非常优美
It's very beautiful.
我喜欢茶叶绽放 翻滚 落下的样子
The way the leaves bloom and float and fall.
我希望我能感受到更深层的东西
I wish I felt something deeper about tea.
我希望我有关于中国茶的真实的记忆
I wish I had a real memory of tea in China.
关于一个地方
Of a place.
关于一段时间的记忆
Of a time.
我觉得这会是…
I think this would...
什么
What?
抱歉 我思路断了
Sorry. I lost my train of thought.
你快乐吗 杨
Are you happy, Yang?
我不知道可不可以问我这个问题
I don't know if that's the question for me.
重放
Repeat.
播放
Play.
我想要被爱…
I want to be loved...
重放
Repeat.
暂停
Pause.
放大
Zoom in.
面容匹配
Face match.
您需要点什么吗
What can I get you?
重拾感官 焕然一新
Our senses, restored, never to be the same.
在耳边低语
Whisper to us.
他们存在过 他们存在过
They existed. They existed.
我们才存在
We can be.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
存在并繁荣 因为他们存在过
Be and be better, for they existed.
玛雅·安杰罗 「当大树倒下」
你觉得那是真的吗
Do you think that's true?
你好?
Hello?
你好 需要点什么吗
Hey, what can I get for you?
你好 你认识她吗
Hey, do you know her?
我不认识
Uh, no, I don't.
你能问一下吗 她之前应该在这里工作
Could you ask someone else? I think she used to work here.
不好意思 还有人在排队
I'm sorry, there's a line.
您需要点些东西
I'm gonna need you to order something.
那来杯双份浓缩
Oh, I'll have a double espresso.
还有我希望能见一下经理
And if I can speak to the manager, that would be great.
双份浓缩 是吧
Double espresso, is that it?
对 还有经理
Yes. And the manager.
抱歉 我帮不了你
Sorry, I can't help you.
但是她之前在这里工作
But she worked here.
她已经不在这里工作了
She doesn't work here anymore.
但你能告诉我她叫什么名字吗
But could you tell me her name?
你为什么要找她
Why do you want to find her?
她认识我儿子
She knew my son.
他现在不太好 身体不太好
And he's not doing so well right now. Health-wise.
我觉得她可能想知道
And I thought she'd want to know.
但你从没见过她
But you've never met her.
嗯
No.
你也不知道她的名字
And you don't know her name.
嗯
No.
好吧 那我也不知道
Yeah. Then I don't either.
抱歉
Sorry.
- 你好  - 你好 乔治
- Hey. - Hey, George.
有什么需要帮忙的吗
What do you need?
我想问问你有没有在这附近见过她
I was wondering if you'd ever seen her around the house.
她是谁
I... Who is she?
不知道 但是杨认识她
I don't know, but Yang knew her.
是吗
Really? Huh.
我都不知道机器…
I... I didn't know that bots, uh...
机器人也可以自己交朋友
That techno beings could make friends on their own.
- 他们只是…  - 我什么都不知道
- They were just... - I... I don't know anything,
我只是想找到她
I just want to find her.
让我问问姑娘们 也许她们知道点什么
Let me ask the girls. Maybe they know something.
拜托了 谢谢
Please. Thank you.
女士们 请过来一下
Ladies, I need to see you.
什么事
What is it?
过来一下 把双胞胎姐妹也带来
Just get over here. And bring the twins.
维姬刚刚入选垒球全明星队
Vicky just made the all-star softball team.
你一定要看 她可厉害了
You gotta come watch. I mean, she's just great.
真不错
Nice.
怎么了
What is it?
弗莱明先生想问你们有没有见过她
Mr. Fleming wants to know if you've seen her around.
确定吗
Are you sure?
我们可以走了吗
Can we go?
可以 回去吧
Yeah. Go ahead.
你呢
How about you?
她遇到什么麻烦了吗
Is she in trouble?
- 我不知…  - 没有 没有
- I don't... - No. No, not at all.
杨怎么样了
How's Yang?
他不太好
He's not so good.
我想找到她 可能可以帮上忙
You know, I think finding her, it might help.
嗯 我见过她
Yeah, I've seen her.
你见过?
You have?
见过几次 在你家
A couple times. At your place.
你和她说过话吗
Did you ever talk to her?
说过一次 杨让我不要说
Once. Yang asked me not to say anything.
为什么
Why?
你不喜欢克隆人吧
You don't like clones, right?
- 不是的  - 维姬 别这么直接
- No, no, it's not... - Come on, Vic. No fastballs.
我只是…我从来没有…
I just... I've never had the...
- 没事  - 有事
- It's... It's fine. - No, it's not.
维姬
Vicky.
她是克隆人
She's a clone.
是吗
She is?
是的 但是她很酷 人也很好 就像我们大部分克隆人一样
Yeah, but she's really cool and nice. Like most of us.
那肯定
I'm sure.
你知道她叫什么名字吗
Um, do you know her name?
叫艾迪还是艾达之类的
It's Aidy or Ada, something like that.
好的 谢谢
Okay. Thank you.
我向你道歉如果我之前…
Look, I'm sorry if I've ever...
我可以走了吗
Can I go now?
可以 谢谢 亲爱的
Yes. Thank you, sweetheart.
我真的很抱歉
I'm... I'm really sorry, it's...
没事 没事 真心的
No, no, no, it's... Honestly.
你应该看看她的投球
You should see her fastball.
她真的是…
I mean, she's just...
可以一整天…
...like, all day long. I mean...
谢谢 乔治 我真的得…
Well, thanks, George. I really have to...
- 下次聊  - 嗯
- Another time. - Yeah.
或者什么时候可以一起喝一杯?
Uh, hey, maybe we can get a drink together, huh? Sometime?
嗯 当然可以
Yeah. Yeah, that'd be great.
我想见哥哥
I want to see gege.
我知道 宝贝
I know, love.
你想他 我也想 但现在没法见他
You miss him. Me, too. We just can't see him now.
那家庭舞蹈大赛怎么办
What about the family dance?
我们再也不能跳了吗
Are we never gonna dance again?
当然不会
Of course we will.
但我们可能要参加三人家庭的比赛了
But we might have to compete in the family of threes.
我不想参加三人家庭的
I don't want to be a family of three!
美香
Mika.
我要哥哥回来
I want gege back!
爸爸正在努力 他正在尽全力
Daddy's trying his best. He's doing everything he can.
我也希望他回来
I want him back, too.
你呢 妈妈 你希望他回来吗
What about you, Mom? Do you want him back?
当然
Of course I do.
这件事实在是拖太久了
This is dragging on too long.
我还需要一点点时间
I just need a little more time.
我们应该开始把注意力放在美香身上了
Oh, we need to start focusing on Mika.
我们这样只会让她更难受的
We're just making things more difficult for her.
杰克 你听到了吗
Jake, do you hear me?
如果我们不能把杨修好的话 我们…
If we can't get Yang fixed, we just...
我们要往前看了 好吗
we need to move forward. Okay?
好了 好了
Now. Now.
我有事情要告诉你
I need to tell you something.
不是 它卡住了
No, it's... it's frozen.
有意思
That's interesting.
试试执行"记忆显示信息"
Try command "memory reveal info,"
它会告诉你有没有损坏
and it should tell you if it's corrupt or not.
好的 我会试一下
Okay, I'll do that.
对了 我在想
Also, I was wondering,
像杨这样的文化机器人
is it possible for cultural technos like Yang to
是不是可能产生感情
want to have romantic potential?
你是说对于使用他们的人类吗
Do you mean for humans to use them?
不不不 我是说杨对其他人…
No, no, no, I mean, for Yang to be interested in...
有个女孩子 她在杨的记忆里
There's a girl, and she showed up in his memories,
而且我们完全不认识她
and, you know, we didn't know anything about her.
真的吗
Really?
太不可思议了
That's fascinating,
因为我从来没有听过文化机器人
because I've never heard of cultural technos
可以有这种能力 你不知道…
having that capacity. I cannot tell you how much...
杨和他的记忆…
...Yang and his memories...
我要过去一下
I should get that.
好吧 不过我们很快会再联络的吧
Oh, all right, okay. But we'll touch base soon?
- 嗯 好的  - 好的
- Yeah, let's do that. - Great.
你在找我吗
You've been looking for me?
对
Yes.
我是杰克
I'm Jake.
我知道
I know.
我是艾达
I'm Ada.
艾达 请进
Ada. Well, come in, please.
我就知道出事了
I knew something was wrong.
我们常常见面 而他不回我信息了
We usually meet, and he wasn't answering my messages.
真抱歉
I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
我知道杨很高兴成为这个家的一份子
I know Yang loves being a part of this family.
我能问问你们是怎么认识的吗
Can I ask how you met?
在咖啡店
At the coffee shop.
他接近你的吗
He approached you?
他是常客
He was a regular customer.
他总是来买东西
He used to buy things all the time, which,
所以当我发现他是机器人之后我觉得很好笑
you know, was funny when I found out he was a techno.
但是 嗯…我们开始聊天 然后…
But, yeah, we started talking, and...
某一次 他问我想不想做点什么事
eventually, he asked me if I wanted to do something.
你和杨…
Were you and Yang...
你们…
Were you guys...
我们从来没有这样说过我们的事
Well, we never really talked about us in that way.
不好意思 那是我太太 我要去…
Sorry, that's... That's my wife. I need to...
- 嗯  - 抱歉
- Yeah. - Sorry.
请你…不要离开
Please... don't leave.
她崩溃了 你得去接她
She's freaking out. You need to pick her up.
她怎么了
What's she doing?
他们说她打了一个孩子
They said she punched a kid,
然后开始对所有人大喊大叫
and then she started screaming at everyone.
- 天呐  - 你现在能去接她吗
- Holy shit. - Are you able to get her now?
可以 我这就出发
Yeah. Uh, yeah. I'm on my way.
谢谢
Thank you.
我想见他
I want to see him.
美香
Mika...
杨非常爱你
Yang loves you so much.
他总是说起你
He always talks about you.
- 谢谢你让我们进来  - 没事 我理解
- Thanks again for this. - Oh, I understand.
相信大家都很想念他
I'm sure everyone misses him a lot.
美香
Mika.
哥哥
Gege.
抱歉 宝贝
I'm sorry, baby.
哥哥
Gege!
他会有自己的一块区域
He would have his own area.
我们会循环播放他的一些记忆
We could put some of his memories on a loop,
大屏播放
projected,
或是给游客提供读卡装置
or on a set of readers that visitors could wear.
当然 每段记忆都会经过你的同意
Of course, any memory would have to be approved by you.
杨
Yang.
播放
Play.
你的收藏越来越多了
Your collection is growing.
哦 你好
Oh, hi.
对 越来越多了
Yes, it's getting bigger.
你希望我到此为止吗 我可以把一部分收起来
Do you want me to stop now? I can put some away.
不用 我不是在抱怨
No, no. I'm not complaining.
我还挺喜欢的
I like them quite a bit.
你知道吗 蝴蝶是
Do you know butterflies were one of
十九世纪中期中国艺术品
the favorite subjects of Chinese trade art
最喜欢的主题之一
in the mid-1800s?
这我不知道
No, I did not know that.
中国人喜爱蝴蝶
The Chinese love butterflies.
还有一个家喻户晓的民间传说
There's also a famous folk tale about two lovers
两个恋人心碎而死 双双化蝶
who die of broken hearts and reemerge as butterflies.
还有 中国古代哲学家老子曾说
Also, the ancient Chinese philosopher Lao Tzu once said,
"毛毛虫眼中的世界末日
"What the caterpillar calls the end,
"我们称之为蝴蝶"
"the rest of the world calls a butterfly."
我喜欢这句话
I like that.
这是你相信的东西吗
Is this something you believe?
- 什么  - 就是结束…
- Hmm? - That the end...
结束也是一种开始
That the end is also a beginning?
也是
...is also
开始
the beginning?
对于毛毛虫来说
For the caterpillar...
对于毛毛虫来说 是的
For the caterpillar, yes.
那你觉得一切都是如此吗
But do you believe it's true for all things?
我不知道
I don't know.
我没有被设定为这样的思维方式
I'm not programmed to believe in that way.
你呢
What about you?
我愿意去相信
I'd like to believe that.
是吗
Do you?
有时候我觉得
Sometimes I think
人类被设定为
humans are programmed
去相信这样的东西 但…
to believe in such things, but...
我不知道这样对我们是不是最好的
I don't know if it's really in our best interest.
我可以和你说实话吗
May I be honest with you?
可以 等等…
Yes. Wait, is...
你可以选择不说实话吗
Is not being honest an option for you?
应该不行吧
I don't think so.
继续
Go on.
我不介意最后化为虚无
I'm fine if there's nothing in the end.
是吗
Are you?
也许我是这样被设定的
Maybe I was programmed this way as well.
你因此感到过伤心吗
Does it ever make you feel sad?
有无相生
There's no something without nothing.
你因此感到过伤心吗
Does it ever make you feel sad?
有无相生
There's no something without nothing.
老子说的?
Lao Tzu?
我不确定
I'm not sure.
杨因为是机器人感到过痛苦吗
Did Yang ever struggle with being a techno?
这是什么意思
What do you mean?
我是说 他是不是曾经想成为人类
I mean, did he ever... want to be human?
什么
What?
没什么
Nothing.
只不过…
It's just...
只有人类才会问这样的问题吧
That's such a human thing to ask, isn't it?
我们总以为其他物种
We always assume that other beings
想要成为人类
would want to be human.
成为人类有什么好呢
What's so great about being human?
所以他从没因此挣扎 从没…有过疑问?
So he never struggled with it? He never... Questioned it?
没对我说过
Not to me.
这样啊
I see.
他确实怀疑过他是不是中国人
He did question if he was Chinese.
是吗
He did?
嗯
Yeah.
怎么样才算是亚洲人
What makes someone Asian?
他总是问这个问题
He'd ask that all the time.
也许他只是想帮美香去明白
Maybe he just wanted to help Mika understand
作为中国人意味着什么
what it means to be Chinese.
他对他妹妹非常用心
He was dedicated to his little sister.
嗯 杨是个好哥哥
Yeah, Yang was a good brother.
他是个特别好的哥哥
He's a great brother.
显示文件信息
Reveal file info.
错误指令 请重试
Wrong command. Try again.
显示记忆信息
Reveal memory info.
允许访问 二级档案
Access granted. Beta archive.
二级档案
Beta archive.
打开
Open.
错误指令 请重试
Wrong command. Try again.
提取
Extract.
完整指令
Full command.
提取二级
Extract beta.
全部播放
Play all.
放大
Zoom in.
坐标
Coordinates.
你好
Hello.
你好 我可以和屋主说话吗
Hi, uh, could I speak to the owners?
可以 稍等
Uh, yes. One moment.
他不只是安静
He wasn't just quiet.
他看起来很沮丧 像是坏了
He seemed despondent. Broken.
几天后我们就把他送了回去
We took him back a few days later,
然后他们给我们换了一个
and they let us make an exchange.
在"兄弟&姐妹"吗
Brothers & Sisters?
不是 那家店是…
No, it was, uh...
名字我不记得了
Well, I can't remember the name.
我们买他的时候不是全新的
We didn't buy him new.
不是吗
You didn't?
不是 但他是官方认证的
No, but he was certified.
"第二个孩子"
Second Siblings.
好像是 是在中国城吗
Maybe. Is that in Chinatown?
嗯 之前是的
Yeah, it used to be.
那你买的时候他是不是已经开机在睡眠状态
I assume he was on when you bought him in a sleep state?
好像是这样的
That sounds right.
提取
Extract
一级
alpha.
空间不足
There is not enough space.
您要压缩二级和三级档案吗
Would you like to compress beta or gamma?
压缩二级
Compress beta.
二级已压缩
Beta compressed.
提取一级
Extract alpha.
空间不足
There is not enough space.
您要压缩三级档案吗
Would you like to compress gamma?
压缩三级
Compress gamma.
三级压缩中
Gamma is compressing.
三级已压缩
Gamma compressed.
提取一级
Extract alpha.
弟弟
Di-di.
你好 弟弟
Ni hao, di-di!
弟弟 醒醒
Di-di, wake up.
弟弟
Di-di.
一切都好吗
Is everything okay?
我们会想你的
We're going to miss you.
你好 我们是来帮助艾玛·戴维森的
Hi, we're here to help Emma Davidson.
是这里 请进
Yes, come in.
慢慢放下
Slowly bring it down.
先一边 再另一边
Side to side.
很好
Good.
你的侄女会喜欢我的
Your niece is going to like me.
我们去抓杨吧 来 抓住他
Hey. Let's go get Yang. Come here. Go get him.
最好不要
You better not.
我可以告诉你一件事吗
Can I tell you something?
快来
Come on!
她是我的叔祖母
She was my great aunt.
你的本体吗
Your original?
杨认识她?
So Yang knew her?
嗯
Yes.
他没告诉过你吗
He never told you?
没有
No.
但我一直在帮忙
But I always helped.
抱歉
Sorry.
我希望他能告诉我她的事 我们的事
I wish he would have told me about her. Us.
是吗
Do you?
他找到你了
He found you.
她睡了
She's asleep.
我不想让杨在博物馆展出了
I don't want Yang to be on display in the museum.
我也是
Neither do I.
但…
But...
我们应该允许他们研究他的记忆
We should let them study his memories.
- 你这么觉得吗  - 嗯 他的存在很重要
- Do you think so? - Yes, his existence mattered.
而且不只是对我们来说
And not just to us.
嗯
Yeah.
哥哥
Gege.
我想谢谢你
I want to thank you
成为这个世界上最好的哥哥
for being the best gege in the world.
对不起
I'm sorry,
我不该说讨厌你
I shouldn't say that I hated you.
我想你了 哥哥
I miss you, gege.
爸爸
Daddy.
你在这里干什么呢
Hey, what are you doing up?
你在干什么呢
What are you doing?
你要喝水吗
You want some water?
来坐我身边吗
Want to sit beside me?
睡不着
Can't sleep.
我也是
Me neither.
不想和哥哥说再见
Don't want to say bye to gege.
我也是
Me neither.
我想成为
I want to be
我想成为一段旋律
I want to be just like a melody
一记声响
Just like a simple sound
一句和声
Like a harmony
♪ Lily Chou
-Chou
- Glide
翻 译  @一个Delpy